Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Flour, Baking Powder, and Baked Goods
  - Box 144.
    - Table and kitchen: a compilation of approved cooking receipts. 57 p., 1915 (Box 144, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Dr Rice's Cream Baking Powder. Provides directions on proper storage of baking powder. Facts worth knowing on the three different kinds of baking powder; tartar, phosphate, alum. Expert testimony from Prof. Vaughan, University of Michigan, on the negative qualities of baking power made with alum. The back cover contains a warning against canvassers from the Alum Baking Powder making misleading claims. Variety of recipes for griddle cakes, breads, fish, soups, meats and poultry, vegetables, puddings, cakes, pies. Sample recipes: Saratoga chips, Bachelors pudding, Brandied peaches.
    - Swan downs flour. [folded brochure], circa 1920s (Box 144, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Swans Down Cake Flour. Illustrations of a variety of cookies and cakes. All recipes use Swans Down cake flour. Sample recipes: Banana nut cake, Butterscotch cookies, Cheese straws.
    - Book of breads. 12 p., 1929 (Box 144, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Cooperative grange league federation exchange. Recipes by Lucile Brewer of Cornell University. Inside cover contains a foreword by H.E. Babcock, General Manager. Hints at making good bread. Variety of recipes for bread making, puddings, cakes, cookies. Sample recipes: Clover leaf rolls, Caramel rolls, Whole wheat spice cakes.
    - Gold medal kitchen guide: recipes-short cuts-household hints. 255 p., 1934 (Box 144, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Mountain City Hill Flour. Kitchen hints on washing greasy dishes, keeping yolks fresh, left over vegetables. Household hints on painting house, washing windows, gas stove burner care. Blank pages for additional recipes. Variety of recipes for fish, eggs and omelets, salads, breads, meats and sauces, vegetables, cakes, pies, sandwiches. Sample recipes: Cream of lima bean, Baked hash, Sandwich fillings.
    - Quick frozen fruits and vegetables. [folded brochure]., 1938 (Box 144, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Polar Brand Frozen Foods. Provides five reasons to purchase Polar brand frozen foods; consumer demands, easy to handle, no waste, no spoilage, sales boosters. List of Polar Brand fruits available and Polar Brand vegetables available. Illustrations include Polar Brand dealer selling woman frozen peas, woman storing vegetables in freezer, woman pouring frozen vegetables into boiling water. No recipes.
    - Good things to eat: henkel's extra fancy flours. 64 p., 1939 (Box 144, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Henkel's Extra Fancy Flour. Provides a table of equivalents for teaspoon, tablespoon, cup, ounce, pound, gill, pint, quart, gallon. Foreword states that the recipes in the book have been both kitchen and laboratory tested. Cover illustration shows a frontier home with a woman baking at a table. Some recipes use wine or liquor as an ingredient. Variety of recipes for cakes, frostings, cookies, pies, muffins. Sample recipes: Yellow angel food cake, Mahogany cake, Peach dumplings.
    - Dreikorn's orange wrap bread: what kind of party shall I give? 32 p., 1939 (Box 144, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Dreikorn's Orange Wrap Bread. Provides the hostess with unusual ideas for her next party. Party themes include bridge party, amateur night party, aviation party, circus party. Three pages are devoted to how to tell fortunes. Cover illustration is of a 1940s hostess asking herself "what kind of a party shall I give"? Sample recipes: Moscow canapés, Boston bean sandwich, Creole dried beef.
    - Celia Lee's centennial baking book. 63 p., 1947 (Box 144, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Centennial Flour. Foreword by Celia Lee, Director for Home Economics Department. Provides general information on flour, leavening agents, shortening, measuring, altitude for baking, yeast making. Photographs of breads, waffles, cookies, cakes. "MS recipe for cookies on back cover." Sample recipes: Brownie bars, Banana nut cake, Standard pancakes.
    - Specialty breads. 144 p., 1948 (Box 144, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes General Mills flour. Provides advice to business owners on the promotion of specialty breads in stores. Statistical data on bread consumption, sales promotion, window displays, budgeting. Background on bread through the ages beginning with prehistoric times and encompassing Egypt, Rome, and its role in the "average American diet." Variety of recipes for fruit breads, rye breads, quick breads, rolls, doughnuts. Sample recipes: Sesame egg twist bread, Fig bread, Orange bread.